I mentioned in the last lecture that action creators can help us, for that I'll create a new subfolder
Son konferansa, aksiyon yaratclarnn maaza klasrnde yeni bir alt klasr oluturacamza yardm
in the store folder,
edebileceinden bahsettim.
I'll name it actions and I move my actions in there,
Eylem adn vereceim ve eylemlerimi oraya tadm.
I'll leave the file as it is for now.
Sonbahar imdilik olduu gibi brakacam.
I move that into the actions folder because we'll also add multiple action files over the next lectures
Bunu eylemler klasrne tadm, nk bir sonraki derslere birden fazla eylem dyor.
but for now, let's stick this one. In there,
Fakat imdilik bunu bir tane yapalm.
we export all our action identifiers and that is working fine.
Tm eylem tanmlayclarmz veriyoruz ve iler yolunda gidiyor.
Now I want to introduce a new way of creating actions, so-called action creators,
imdi, Eylem yaratclar diye adlandrlan eylemleri yaratmann yeni bir yolunu tantmak istiyorum.
how does that look like? What is that? An action creator
Bu ection yaratcs neye benziyor?
is just a function which returns an action or which creates an action, hence the name.
Bir eylemi geri getiren veya adna kar bir eylem yaratan bir ilevdir.
We right now create our actions hardcoded in our code or simply when we need them
imdi, eylemlerimizi kodumuza sabit kodlanm olarak veya yalnzca onlara ihtiya duyduumuzda yaratyoruz.
I should say, in the counter component. Here
Burada saya bileeninde sylemeliyim.
on mapDispatchToProps, the actions,
Haritada eylemlerin pervanesine gnderilmesi.
these are just these javascript objects, right?
Bunlar sadece Deese javascript nesneleridir.
We create them here, we create them by simply writing the code for the object into our dispatch function.
Onlar, sadece nesnenin kodunu gnderme ilevimize yazarak yaratyoruz.
An action creator would return such an object and you can see the benefit when we talk about asynchronous
yaratcs byle bir nesneyi dndrr ve ezamansz kod hakknda konuurken fayda grrsnz.
code.
Eylem
So let's create an action creator right now
imdi bir eylem yaratcs oluturalm.
for synchronous code though. For that, I'll create a new function and you can use the function keyword
Bunun iin senkron kod olsa da yeni bir ilev oluturacam ve anahtar kelimeyi
or create an arrow function and I'll name it increment,
ilemek iin kullanabilir veya ok ilevini yaratabilirsiniz ve ona artm ad vereceim.
the convention is to use the same name as your identifier
Szleme, tanmlaycnzla ayn ad kullanmanzdr.
but in camel case, so lowercase character first. Increment is an arrow function as I said,
Ama deve durumda kk harf karakteri ilk art bir takm olarak bir ilevdir.
it will return something eventually and it will receive something, it can receive something I should
Eninde sonunda bir eyler dnecek ve alabilecei bir ey alacak.
say, it receives any payloads you want to pass with that action. Here for increment,
Sana sylemeliyim ki bu eylemle birlikte gemek istediin yk arttrmak iin burada.
I don't want to pass any,
Hibirini gemek istemiyorum.
so instead I just return something and that something is the actions or javascript object.
Bunun yerine ben sadece bir ey dndrr ve eylemlerin veya javascript nesnesinin bir ey olduunu.
Now as any action, it has to have a type and the type should be increment,
Artk herhangi bir eylem olarak bir tr ve tr olmas gerekir.
referring to our identifier. Previously, I did this in the counter.js
nceden tanmlaycmza atfta bulunmak bu saylmaz.
file here, increment which I imported from action types by reaching out that actions file.
Eylem trlerini ie aktardm art, eylemleri drmek iin uzatarak ulan.
Now I actually can't get rid of that import and we will have to change what we dispatch here soon.
Aslnda o ithalattan kurtulamyorum ve ksa srede sevk ettiim eyi deitirmeliyiz.
For now let's go back to the actions.js file,
imdilik, de geri dnelim.
this is our first action creator already,
Bu, ilk eylemimiz Yaratc zaten zaten.
it returns,
Geri dnd.
it creates therefore an action and an action just needs to have a type, so that's the bare minimum action
Bu nedenle bir eylem oluturur ve sadece bir tre sahip olmas gereken bir eylem
we can create.
Yani, oluturabileceimiz minimum eylem budur.
We can use this action creator now in the counter.js file where we do dispatch it by first of
imdi bu eylem yaratcs kullanabiliriz ve kar koyucular, bu yamay yaptmz yerde, nce onu
all importing it.
ie aktararak dyorlar.
So here I'll import something from this actions file,
Dolaysyla, burada gerekletirilen ilemlerden bir eyler ie aktaracam.
so I'll navigate up to the store folder into actions and there to the actions.js file. Now in there,
Dolaysyla maaza klasrne gidip eylemler haline geleceim ve oraya sadece u andaki eylemleri izleyeceim ve
I need to go back to it,
ona geri dneceksiniz.
I need to export this increment function.
Bu artm ilevini da aktarmam gerekiyor.
Now I can import it by name
imdi adyla ie aktarabilirim.
so in the counter.js file, I can import increment and keep in mind, this is a function.
Yani, saya js dosyasnda artm ie aktarabilir ve bunun bir ilev olduunu gz nnde bulundurabilirim.
Now we can use that function in the counter.js file
imdi bu ilevi J sayacnda sonbahar gibi kullanabiliriz.
at the bottom where we map our props to dispatch functions. For increment
Alt ksmda art iin ilevler gndermek iin sahne haritas yapyoruz.
here, I will now simply pass increment like that and also execute it
Burada art sadece dat gibi geirip de uygulayacam.
because once I execute increment and this will happen when this prop is basically executed, when I execute
nk bir kez artm uyguladm ve art uyguladmda bu pervane temelde yrtldnde
increment,
gerekleecektir.
this will give me an action because it's an action creator, don't forget that, increment returns us
Bu bana bir eylem verecektir, nk bu eylem art bir eylem olarak geri dndrr unutmayn ya
an action,
da unutmayn.
so we execute it, we get an action.
Bu yzden idam ettik, bir eylem olsun.
Now that's very nice,
Bu ok gzel
our application is still broke though because all the other actions here are not connected.
Buradaki dier tm eylemler bal olmad iin bavurumuz hala krlyor.
So what I'll quickly do is I'll create more action creators for all the actions or to be precise,
Bu yzden hzl bir ekilde ne yapacam, tm gerek veya tecrbesiz yaratclar daha fazla ticaret yapacam.
you should do this.
Bunu yapmalsn.
So here is your challenge,
te size meydan okumanz.
create action creators like this one for all the actions and see if you can figure out how to handle
Bunun gibi eylem yaratclarn tm eylemler iin oluturun ve gerekten bir yk gerektiren eylemlerin
the actions which actually need a payload.
nasl ele alnabileceini renin.
We'll do it together in the next video.
Bunu bir sonraki videoda birlikte yapacaz.